<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and death of Dorcas VVherein, hee that pleaseth to reade, may finde both good direction for the ordering of his course: and a necessary warning to be prepared for his end. By Samuel Hieron.</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851245</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851245</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16515</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16515)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1106:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and death of Dorcas VVherein, hee that pleaseth to reade, may finde both good direction for the ordering of his course: and a necessary warning to be prepared for his end. By Samuel Hieron.</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melch. Bradwood for Samuel Macham, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Bullhead,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A funeral sermon.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dorcas --  (Biblical figure), --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16515:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16515:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF DORCAS.</p>
            <p>VVHEREIN, HEE that pleaſeth to reade, may finde both good direction for the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his Courſe: AND A neceſſary warning to be prepared for his End.</p>
            <p>By SAMVEL HIERON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm. 92. ver. 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The righteous ſhall flouriſh like a Palme tree, and ſhall grow like a Cedar in Lebanon.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by MELCH. BRADWOOD for SAMVEL MACHAM, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Bulhead. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16515:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16515:2"/>
            <head>TO MY MVCH HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lady, the Ladie MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GARET HELE of Weu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie in Deuon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame, many things, which I haue obſerued in you, do euen aſſure me, that this ſmall preſent ſhall finde ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with you: theſe two eſpecially; your reuerent estimation of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God (the word preached) and your more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reſpect vnto my miniſtrie: Other things I could name, but that I do abhorre the very ſmell and ſhadow of flatterie. It hath pleaſed you ſome time, to craue of me the notes of ſome things which I haue (in your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring) taught in publique: Being much deſired by many to commit to printing, that which God enabled mee very lately to deliuer, at the funerals of a worthy gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-woman of theſe parts, I thought to inſcribe it vnto your Ladie-ſhips name, as a pledge of my true deſire to further you (all I may) in your iourney towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. The matter is, of a woman, in the Scripture well reported of, both for her holy profeſsion, and for her
<pb facs="tcp:16515:3"/>
gracious fruit, to whom the more like your Ladie-ſhip ſhall become, the better ſhall your aſſurance be of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into reſt: I commend the Sermon to your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the perſon treated of to your Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your bodie and ſoule to the protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, my ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladie-ſhips ready ſeruitor in any Chriſtian office SAM. HIERON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:16515:3"/>
            <p>Tabitha, or Dorcas of Ioppa, her
<list>
                  <item>life: in which her
<list>
                        <item>Profeſſion: A Diſciple</item>
                        <item>Fruit:
<list>
                              <item>Generall full of
<list>
                                    <item>Good workes.</item>
                                    <item>Almes.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>Particular full of
<list>
                                    <item>Good workes.</item>
                                    <item>Almes.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>death: ſhe
<list>
                        <item>was ſicke.</item>
                        <item>died.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16515:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16515:4"/>
            <head>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF DORCAS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS 9.36.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There was alſo at Ioppa a certaine woman, a Diſciple named Tabitha, (which by interpretation is called Dorcas) ſhee was full of good workes and almes which ſhee did.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And it came to paſſe in thoſe daies, that ſhee was ſicke and died.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His which I haue read is the entrance into a very memorable ſtorie,<note place="margin">The generall ſtate of the place.</note> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a teſtimonie which God gaue to the word of his grace, by enabling <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to reſtore a dead woman vnto life. I am now to treat of it, as an entire par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in itſelfe, and being ſo conſidered, I may terme it, A compendious or briefe report of the life and death of a certaine worthy Matron, whoſe dwelling was in <hi>Ioppa,</hi> whoſe name, in the Syriacke tongue, <hi>Tabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> as much in effect as that which in Greeke is called <hi>Dorcas:</hi> a name very honourable now becauſe it was hers, though in it owne natiue ſignification not ſo gracefull, it being as much to ſay as in Engliſh, <hi>Roe,</hi> or <hi>Goat:</hi> no more preiudice to her who was a ſheepe of Chriſts, then it was behoouefull to traiterous <hi>Abſhalom</hi> that by the purport of his name he was the father of peace. I will not ſpend
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16515:5"/>
time about theſe circumſtances of her name and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, though both might aſtoord vs good matter of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: the one, to ſhew how that (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. God ſaid to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>) <note n="a" place="margin">Ex. 33 17.</note> the relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous finde that fauour in the ſight of God, that he knoweth them by name, and that, although it bee their portion heere to haue their <hi>names put out as euill</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Luk 6 22.</note>, yet ſtill they are <hi>written in heauen</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20.</note>, <hi>in the Booke of life of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Deu. 13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, out of which <hi>they ſhall neuer bee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3.5.</note>, whereas the wicked though they thinke <hi>to get them a name</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 11.4.</note>, and lay plots <hi>to keepe their name in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">2. Sam. 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, and to that end doe <hi>call their Lands by their names</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſ. 49 11.</note>, yet their <hi>name ſhall not</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 10 7.</note>, and ſhall <hi>bee left by them as a curſe vnto Gods choſen</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 65.15.</note>: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of her dwelling might bee brought to minde vs, that the Lord <hi>knoweth our dwelling</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 27.28. Reu. 2.13.</note>, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is <hi>accustomed to all our wates</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 139.3.</note>. If we walke in obedience before him, no place can hinder our accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him: his ere is as well to <hi>Ioppa</hi> as to <hi>Ieruſalem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and if wee <hi>walke ſtubbornly against him</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Leuit. 26.23.</note>, no place can throud vs from his hand. For, <hi>Whither ſhall wee flee from his preſence?</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 139 7.</note> And, <hi>The e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Lord in euery place ſhall behold the euill and the good</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 15.3.</note>. Thoſe things I could vrge from theſe circumſtances: but becauſe I am now like to a poore traueller, that hath farre to goe and little to ſpend, much matter before me in my text, but not much time before me to deliuer it in, I will therefore ſelect ſuch things as may ſort with the purpoſe of our meeting, which as it is to ſolemnize the funerall of a deceaſed Matrone, ſo it ſhould bee to take occaſion thereby, ſo to <hi>number our daies that we applie our hearts to wiſedome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 90.12</note>, and ſo to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our daies by <hi>paſſing the time of our dwelling heere in feare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, that (which is the reward of godlineſſe) God may <hi>doe vs good in our latter end</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u 8.16.</note> I come therefore to thoſe two generall points, the <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Dorcas,</hi> the one,<note place="margin">The diuiſion in the place into 2. parts.</note> verſ. 36. the other, verſ. 37. Touching her life, there are two things conſiderable: 1. Her profeſſion <hi>(a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16515:5"/>
Diſciple):</hi> 2. The fruits of her profeſſion <hi>(full of good workes &amp;c.):</hi>
               <note place="margin">The things conſiderable in the firſt part.</note> two things which ought to kiſſe each other in the life of a Chriſtian. A profeſſion without fruit, is groſte hypocriſie? A kind of fruit (for ſo there may be) without a right profeſſion, is boote leſſe formalitie: but both together, knowledge to guide obedience, and ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience to teſtifie the truth of the knowledge, that is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. In whom I can finde theſe two, of him I may ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Behold indeed an Iſraelite in whom is no guile</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 1.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>? This is the man of <hi>pure heart, and innocent hands,</hi> that ſhall <hi>aſcend into the mountaine of the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 21.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>. Let me ſpeake of both a-part, I may diuide them in my diſcourſe, but in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r courſe, neither you nor I, may ſunder them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Her profeſſion, a <hi>Diſciple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The 1. thing in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part.</note> Diſciple was the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>marie name by which thoſe that profeſſed the truth were called in the prime daies of the Goſpell. In the beginning it was a title more pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uliar to thoſe that gaue their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie attendance vpon our Sauiour: The twelue Apoſtles are called the <hi>twelue Diſciples</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 10 1.</note>; but yet euen then, the name was enlarged, his ordinarie hearers are called his <hi>Diſciples</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ioh 6.66.</note> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of Arimathea, is ſaid to haue beene a <hi>Diſciple</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 19 38.</note>. After Chriſts aſcenſion, as the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of beleeuers was enlarged, ſo the name grew more common: as in this very chapter, the true profeſſors whom <hi>Saul</hi> did perſecute, are called <hi>the Diſciples of the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ver. 1.</note>, <hi>Ananias</hi> is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmed a <hi>Diſciple</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ver. 10.</note>, and thoſe which were after at <hi>Antioch,</hi> called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (where that name was firſt taken vp,) were before that time called <hi>Diſciples</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 11 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. A <hi>Diſciple</hi> is as much to ſay in Engliſh as a learner, and the beleeuers were ſo ſtiled becauſe they were ſuch, as in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ſauing knowledge had their dependance vpon the ordinarie meanes of inſtruction, (the preaching of the word.) So then, <hi>Dorcas</hi> a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> that is <hi>Dorcas</hi> a ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in the ſchoole of Chriſt, a ſubmitter of herſelfe to the ordinance of God for the ſauing of her ſoule. Shee was none of thoſe <hi>Learners</hi> whom the Apoſtle blameth, which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16515:6"/>
               <hi>learne to go about from houſe to houſe &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.13.</note> but ſuch a <hi>Learner</hi> as <hi>Lydia,</hi> which <hi>attended to thoſe things which were ſpoken of Paul</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Acts. 16.14.</note>. Her being a <hi>Learner,</hi> is (as other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) <hi>written for our learning</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 15 4. The 1. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note>, and the Doctring which it affordeth to vs, is this. <hi>That, to be a learner of religion by the meanes ordained of God, to teach religion is a part of the very eſſence and Being of a Chriſtian.</hi> Theſe two words a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> are as wee are wont to ſay in ſchooles, termes conuertible, as thus; <hi>If a Diſciple, ſurely a Chriſtian: If a Chriſtian, ſurely a Diſciple: If no Diſciple, no Chriſtian: If no Chriſtian, no Diſciple.</hi> I know there be alſo many counterfet Diſciples, and ſo there be alſo many counterfet Chriſtians, and many ſeeme to be Diſciples, which yet are no Chriſtians, and many alſo take vpon them to be Chriſtians, which by no meanes will be Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: yet ſtil doth that which I haue ſaid remaine true, that, ſuch as is a mans <hi>Diſciple-ſhip,</hi> ſuch is his <hi>Chriſtianitie:</hi> If a true <hi>Diſciple,</hi> a true <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> if but a formall <hi>Diſciple,</hi> ſurely but an hollow <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> I will appeale to any mans iudgement, be it that he be but (as it were) a man of <hi>yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iob. 8 9.</note> in Religion, to tell mo, what other thing is ment, by this, that <hi>Dorcas</hi> was a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> then this <hi>Dorcas was a belieuer, a woman conuerted by the Goſpell, to the Chriſtian Faith?</hi> So that this obſeruation is iuſt from hence, <hi>Either a Diſciple, or elſe, no Chriſtian.</hi> To this for a fuller confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation we may ioine that ſpeach of Chriſts to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when he ſent them out to preach: <hi>Go, and teach all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> or word for word from the <hi>Greeke, go make them Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 28.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If you can bring them once to this, to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be taught of God in his owne ordinance, you haue won them.</hi> When our Sauiour would ſhew what marke his ſheepe haue, he declareth it to be an <hi>Eare-marke, my ſheepe heare my voice</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 10.27.</note>, they haue the <hi>wiſe and obedient eare</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Prou. 25.12.</note>, Now a good <hi>Hearer</hi> and a good <hi>Diſciple</hi> are all one. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, No man can be a <hi>Chriſtan</hi> indeed, vnleſſe he be a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer: for what is a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but a man in <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.17.</note>, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16515:6"/>
how cometh that vnion betwixt a man and Chriſt but by <hi>Faith</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note>? and how ſhall a man haue <hi>Faith,</hi> but by being a <hi>Diſciple? Faith is by hearing</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom 10.17.</note>, and <hi>Hearing</hi> is the inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable quality of a <hi>Diſciple:</hi> Further what <hi>Chriſtian</hi> will you call him, that ſhall not be ſaued, and what Saluation is there for him, that forſaketh that olde beaten path, <hi>Heare, and your ſoule ſhall liue</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 55 3.</note>. Beſides, how is hee a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that doth <hi>not know God, and him whom he hath ſent Chriſt Ieſus</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 17, 3.</note>, and who can know ſo much vnleſſe he be a <hi>Diſciple?</hi> man of himſelfe doth not know it, (for, <hi>euery man is a beaſt by his owne knowledge</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ier. 10.14</note>, Man of himſelfe cannot know it, (for it <hi>is fooliſhneſſe vnto him</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note>: hee muſt attaine to it by donation from God, or elſe he can neuer vnderſtand it, (for <hi>a man can receiue nothing except it bes giuen from aboue</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 3.27.</note>: If he muſt expect it from God, beggers muſt not chuſe, and hee muſt fit himſelfe ſo to receiue it, as God is pleaſed to beſtow it, and he will not beſtow it but by <hi>the folly of preaching</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note>: a man muſt ſit him downe in the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> forme, or hee ſhall neuer obtaine it. I know the world will account him but a foole who tieth himſelfe to this courſe, but this is that <hi>Fooliſhneſſe of God,</hi> which <hi>is wiſer then Men</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.25.</note> and he who ſeemeth to be <hi>wiſe in this world,</hi> muſt <hi>be a foole, that he may be wiſe</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.18.</note>. This briefely, to cleere this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Now, for vſe, if none be <hi>Chriſtians</hi> but <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and none <hi>Diſciples,</hi> but ſuch as haue choſen <hi>Maries</hi> part, to <hi>ſit at Ieſus feet to heare his preaching</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Luk. 10.39.</note>, and what <hi>Feet</hi> are there now left vnto vs but <hi>thoſe beautifull ones, which bring glad tidings of peace</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note>? Tell mee then (I pray you) what plentie is there of <hi>Christians?</hi> Sure I am, the number of <hi>Diſciples</hi> is not great. I know, <hi>Hearers</hi> there bee many, but not euery <hi>Hearer</hi> a <hi>Diſciple.</hi> By that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Diſciples</hi> are ſhoaled out from the great preaſe and multitude of common <hi>Hearers,</hi> I will tell you how it will be. <hi>Iſrael</hi> went out to fight againſt <hi>Aram: Iſrael</hi> pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16515:7"/>
on the one ſide, <hi>Aram</hi> on the other ſide: <hi>The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael were like two little flockes of Kids, but the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes filled the Countrey</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> Heere is the very true pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portion betwixt the great ſwarmes of <hi>Hearers,</hi> and the ſmall handfull of <hi>Diſciples.</hi> There bee many things doe make men <hi>Hearers,</hi> as, neceſſitie, authoritie, hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alitie, affectat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of noueltie, &amp;c. But there is but one thing makes a man a <hi>Diſciple;</hi> a ſettled perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that, that whereto a man ſubmitteth himſelfe as a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> is the very <hi>Arme of the Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note>, and <hi>the power of God vnto ſaluation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.16</note>. And if we bring <hi>Diſciples</hi> to this ſcantling. I beſeech you aske the men in your own coats, where wee ſhall finde them. Surely the men of this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration are not yet poſſeſſed with the neceſſitie of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance vpon that <hi>Teaching</hi> courſe which the Lord hath ſanctified to the <hi>gathering together of his Saints</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.2</note>. The multitude paſſeth it ouer in a kinde of careleſneſſe, not ſo much as euer putting to the queſtion, <hi>what is to bee done that they may bee ſaued.</hi> They follow the drone: if it bee right, ſo it is; if not, then God helpe, if ſo many ſhall bee damned. But now the wiſer ſort, they conſent and agree, that ſomewhat muſt bee knowen and beleeued vnto ſaluation: but to goe to ſchoole to a Miniſter, to <hi>giue attendance at the pests of the Lords doores,</hi> there to <hi>heare instruction</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note>, that is too ſubmiſſe a courſe: <hi>Why? cannot wee informe ourſelues?</hi> And, <hi>Is there no Chriſtianity, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by ſo ſeruile a conformitie as the hanging vpon the mouth of a Preacher?</hi> No (beloued) either ſhew th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe a <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> or neuer thinke thou art a <hi>Christian</hi> They which were firſt called <hi>Christians,</hi> were <hi>Diſciples</hi> firſt. Neither is euery one a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> which putteth his foot into the Schoole. Hee that commeth with a den all of himſelfe, with an heart hungring after knowledge, with the ſpirit of meekeneſſe, with ſubmiſſion to the ordinance of him who is the onely Doctour of his Church, this is the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi> hee is the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> indeede; this is hee whom <hi>the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16515:7"/>
Lord will guide in iudgement,</hi> and to whom hee will <hi>teach his way</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſa. 25 9.</note>. And thus for the firſt flower which I haue plucked from that garland, with which it hath pleaſed the ſpirit of God to adorne this Matrones name (<hi>Dorcas</hi> a <hi>Diſciple.</hi>) And albeit the world neglects both this title, and the thing intended by it as vnworthy, yet without it wee lay all our honour in the duſt. This title muſt bee a mans glory to the end, as was ſaid of him, <hi>Mnaſon an old Diſciple</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 23 16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;</hi>
               </note>. <hi>As I grow old, ſo I learne ſtill,</hi> ſaid a wiſe Heathen. A man muſt neuer thinke to be preferred out of this Schoole, vntill hee come to bee admitted into that great Vniuerſitie, where hee which is the <hi>Doctour of the Chaire,</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, will aduance all thoſe that haue beene good Proficients in the learners Forme, to <hi>ſit with him vpon his owne Throne</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Reu. 3.21.</note>. So much for her profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Now follow the fruits of her profeſſion:<note place="margin">The 2 thing in the 1. part.</note> of which the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh firſt generally <hi>(full of good workes)</hi> and then ſome particular good workes are made mention of, <hi>(Almes, &amp;c.)</hi> I will treat of both ſunderly: and firſt of this <hi>(full of good workes.)</hi> My order muſt bee thus: Firſt, to ſhew the meaning: Secondly, to ſet downe the doctrine. In the meaning, firſt, what thoſe things are which are called <hi>Good workes:</hi> ſecondly, what it is to bee <hi>full of good workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Good workes</hi> are of the ſame wideneſſe with Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.<note place="margin">What be good works.</note> For obedience to any branch of Gods commandements, is a <hi>good worke.</hi> Papiſts (and from them others) doe ſtraiten the largeneſſe of <hi>good workes,</hi> of which notwithſtanding they take vpon them to bee the chiefeſt Patrones. They goe not much further, then to <hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> and <hi>Faſting,</hi> and ſuch like. The rule of <hi>good workes</hi> is Gods reuealed will <note n="i" place="margin">Mich. 6.8.</note>: voluntarie ſeruices God eſteemeth not <note n="k" place="margin">Col. 2.23.</note>: the <hi>Feare taught by the precepts of men,</hi> he accounts it but hypocriſie <note n="l" place="margin">Iſai. 29.13.</note>. The particular heads of <hi>good workes</hi> are ſet downe, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. 1. <hi>Sobrietie</hi> (in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16515:8"/>
vſe of outward things, meat, drinke, wealth, apparell, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. 2. <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> (in dealings with men, that there be <hi>no oppreſſing, no defrauding</hi>) <note n="m" place="margin">1. Theſ.</note>. 3. <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> (in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters belonging to God, that wee worſhip the true God, after a true manner, with a true heart.) The credit and triall of <hi>good works</hi> ſtandeth in theſe particular: 1. When they are guided by <hi>Knowledge</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note>: (blinde zeale is with God of no eſteeme.) 2. When they are directed to Gods <hi>Glorie</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor 10.31.</note>: (to doe things to be ſeene of men is Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.) 3. When they are carried with a ioint reſpect to all <hi>Gods commandements</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 119.6.</note>: (to be preciſe in ſome things, and in other to take libertie is groſſe hypocriſie) 4. When there is a care chiefly had to thoſe good offices which concerne a mans perſonall calling <note n="q" place="margin">Luk 3 12. &amp;c.</note>: (hee that is not good in a calling, is not good at all.) 5. When they are held out with conſtancie <note n="r" place="margin">Reu 2 10.</note>: (good is not good, if it bee not perpetuall.) This is in few words the true ſtate of <hi>good Workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What to be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll of good workes.</note>Now to be <hi>Full,</hi> hath reference firſt to the ſinceritie of her heart, without which, bee the ſhew to the world-ward neuer ſo glorious, yet a man is but an emptie Chriſtian. 2. to the vniuerſalitie of her practiſe, who like <hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, walked in all the Commandements of God</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Luk. 1 6.</note>. 3. To the forwardneſſe of her diſpoſition, ſhe was <hi>ready to good workes.</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Tit 3 1.</note>. 4. To the vnweariedneſſe of her courſe, ſhe was like <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atira,</hi> her <hi>workes moe at the laſt then at the firſt</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Reu. 2 19.</note>. This is the fulneſſe of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> without fraud, without halting, without grudging, and without tiring. Thus for the meaning. This her <hi>Fulneſſe</hi> affoords ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of matter. But I am forced at this time, in ſtead of a bill of particulars, which in this caſe would be very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, to preſent all in one groſſe ſumme, thus, That euery <hi>Diſciple</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt <hi>accompanie his holy profeſſion with good workes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The 2. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> The ſpirit of God acquainteth vs here what <hi>Dorcas</hi> was, that from thence wee might learne what we muſt be. <hi>Fulneſſe of good workes,</hi> was not in her a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16515:8"/>
matter of ſupererogation but of duty. If it were duty in her, it is neceſſitie in vs. The Scripture abounds in proofe. It was the common charge giuen by <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> to his hearers, when they began to make a good profeſſion, <hi>Bring forth therefore fruit &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat 3.3.</note>. The like elſewhere, <hi>Let your conuerſation be ſuch as becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note>, <hi>Walke worthy the calling whereunto you are called</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 4.1.</note>. It is that which <hi>Paul</hi> preached to the Gentiles <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 26.20.</note>, and hee commanded it to be preſſed by preachers vpon all profeſſors <note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 3.8.</note>. This was he ſuter for to God on their behalfe with whom he laboured <note n="c" place="margin">Col. 1.9.10.</note>. Your conuerts and profeſſors of the new Teſtament of ſpeciall note, their <hi>Good woorkes</hi> are ſpecified; as <hi>Mathew:</hi> his generall woorke is mentioned, <hi>hee followed Christ</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Math. 9 9.</note>: his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, as of <hi>Bounty (he made Ieſus a feast</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">10.</note>,) and of <hi>Charity,</hi> he inuited his fellow <hi>Publicanes</hi> to bee gueſts, that they alſo might be ſaued. <hi>Zacheus, Behold Lord, the halfe of my goods &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 19.8.</note>, There were his workes. The three thouſand brought to be <hi>Diſciples</hi> by <hi>Peters</hi> Miniſtrie, <hi>They continued in the Apoſtles Doctrine, and fellowſhip &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 2.45.46.47.</note>, Theſe were there workes. <hi>Cornelius, his praiers and almes came vp into remembrance with God</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 10.4.</note>, Such were his workes. The beleeuers at Epheſus came and confeſſed and <hi>ſhewed their workes</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 10 18.</note>. <hi>Paul</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Romanes for their <hi>Holineſſe</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 6.22.</note>, the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> for their zeale <note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.11</note>, the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> for their <hi>diligent loue &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Th. 1.3. &amp;c.</note>: Behold a cloud of <hi>witneſſes: whatſoeuer things are honest, and of good report &amp;c. thoſe do</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note>, If theſe things were memorable in others, ſurely they are imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in vs. Why <hi>Good workes</hi> ought to be coupled with our good profeſſion, there bee (as ſaith the Apoſtle) certaine <hi>neceſſary vſes</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Tit. 3.14.</note>, as namely, Firſt, the <hi>Glory of God</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Math. 5.16. Ioh. 15.8.</note>, It is an honour to God, when his ſeruants by profeſſion are as zealous of good workes, as god-leſſe people are in wickedneſſe. Secondly, the conuerſion of others. <note n="q" place="margin">1. Pet 2.12.</note>. It is poſſible that they which reſpect not the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16515:9"/>
word, may <hi>without the Word bee wonne by the pure conuerſation of beleeuers</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1.</note>. Thirdly, the ſtopping of the mouthes of gaineſayers <note n="ſ" place="margin">Tit. 2 8.</note>. The credit of the Goſpell muſt be deare vnto vs, and woe to him which maketh <hi>that worthy name by which he is named to be blaſphemed</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Iam. 2.7.</note>. Fourthly, the declaration of the Truth of our <hi>Faith</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2.18.</note>. It is no liuing but a titular <hi>Faith,</hi> which doth not <hi>worke by Loue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5 6.</note>. Fifthly, aſſurance of our owne Election to our ſoules <hi rend="sup">y</hi>. Good workes are the <hi>Way,</hi> which <hi>God hath ordained vs to to walke in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> Thus you ſee the truth of this aſſertion: A true <hi>Diſciple</hi> muſt not be like the <hi>Tree</hi> which Chriſt curſed, which had leaues but no fruit <note n="a" place="margin">Math. 21.19</note>, but like the <hi>Tree planted by the riuers ſide, that will bring foorth her fruit in due ſeaſon</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ 1.3.</note>, nay, which <hi>bringeth forth her fruite in the age thereof, and is then fat and flowriſhing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.13. The vſe.</note>.</p>
            <p>This is an excellent doctrine and a neceſſarie, and if I were as <hi>eloquent and mightie in the Scriptures,</hi> as <hi>Apollos</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act 18.24.</note>, as <hi>full of the holie Ghoſt,</hi> as <hi>Barnabas</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 11.24.</note>, as <hi>abounding in Faith and power,</hi> as <hi>Steuen</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 6.8.</note>, or had the beſt gift in perſwading, that God hath giuen vnto any, I might well imploy it, in the furthering and promoting of this one point: that we would make conſcience to be <hi>ſuitfull in good workes</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note>. It is an exhortation which many amongſt vs do much need. For albeit the profeſſion of the Goſpell in this kingdome hath not been vnfruitfull, ſo that, for publique euidences of charitie, and monuments of zeale to pietie and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we need not feare to conteſt with the greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites to our Religion, <note n="*" place="margin">See to this end Willet in his <hi>Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſis</hi> pag. 960. &amp;c.</note> beſides the blameleſſe and honeſt conuerſation of many priuate Chriſtians, whoſe liues no doubt, <hi>do adorne the doctrine of God our Sauiour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.10.</note>, which they profeſſe: Yet put caſe we heer for our parts, who as the Iewes of old, <hi>gloried in God</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 2.17.</note>, ſo do alſo boaſt in our profeſsion, and in the ſtile and name of Chriſtianitie, put caſe we (I ſay) be dealt with in particular, may we not iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be challenged for our ſcarcitie of good workes, what better deeds haue many of vs, <hi>then the crying ſinnes of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16515:9"/>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 18.20.</note>, <hi>then the vnfruitfull workes of Darkeneſſe</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 5 11.</note>, contempt of Gods ſacred word and worſhip, blaſpheming of his <hi>glorious and fearefull name</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Deu 28.58</note> prophanation of his holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, whoredome, pride, malice, drunkenneſſe, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſacrilege, and ſuch like. Whom would it not grieue that hath in him the affections of a Chriſtian, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be in ſo generall a diſgrace as this one thing, <hi>to be zealous of good workes,</hi> and that <hi>the working out of our ſaluation with feare and trembling</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note>, which is euen the pith and marrow of all <hi>good workes,</hi> ſhould be a matter by prophane mouthes ſo much ſpoken againſt. I beſeech you, let vs ſuffer the words of exhortation, and let vs be euen emulous of that praiſe which is heer giuen vnto <hi>Dorcas, to be full of good workes.</hi> What an happie, and royall exchange were it, if the fulneſſe of theſe times, fulneſſe of ſecuritie, <hi>Fulneſſe of bread</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ezek. 16 49</note>, might be turned into <hi>Fulneſſe of good workes.</hi> This would be our comfort in death, this would giue vs boldneſſe in the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Death is the worlds ſtrict doore-keeper, and will ſee that as <hi>we brought nothing into the World,</hi> ſo <hi>we carrie no thing out</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.7.</note>, but yet the concomitance of <hi>good Workes</hi> it cannot hinder, <hi>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord, their workes follow them</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Reu. 14 13.</note>: and for the day of Iudgement, our triall there, ſhall not be by our profeſſion, but by <hi>our Workes,</hi> and euery man ſhall be remembred there accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his goodneſſe heere. Thinke not I preach <hi>Good-Worke,</hi> like a Iuſticiarie. I confeſſe when we haue done all we muſt ſay, <hi>we are vnprofitable ſeruants</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk. 17.50.</hi> Niſi Deus per miſericordiam part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, non haberet. qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s per iuſtiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> coronaret. Auguſt in Pſ. <hi>100.</hi>
               </note>, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge with that ancient Father, that vnleſſe God did ſpare in mercie, he ſhould find none whom he might crowne in iuſtice. It is ſaid of <hi>Manlius Torquatus,</hi> that when his ſonne contrarie to a martiall decree, had exceeden his courſe, and ſlaine an enemie, his father, being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the ſeruice, firſt crowned him for his valour, and then executed him for his diſobedience. So may God deale with vs, were it that he ſhould find any thing in vs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16515:10"/>
worthy to bee rewarded, hee ſhould withall finde more then ſomething deſeruing to be puniſhed. Now though I th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſclaime the merit of <hi>Good Workes,</hi> and crie with him that ſaid,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> 
               <hi>My men it is the Lords mercie;</hi> yet I main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the neceſſitie of <hi>Good Workes.</hi> For them, no man ſhall be ſaued: but without them, there is no entring into reſt. <hi>Follow holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> The way to heauen is an <hi>holy way,</hi> and <hi>the pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhall not paſſe by it</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 35.8.</note>. Let vs therfore <hi>caſt away our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. 18.31</note>, <hi>mortifie our members, that are on earth</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note>, <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our fleſh, with the affections and luſts</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note>, <hi>make our waies and our workes good</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 18.11.</note>, if wee deſire in our life to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in our death to be comforted, and at the laſt reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to bee crowned. So much touching the generall fruit of <hi>Dorcas</hi> profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What Almes 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>One particular of her <hi>Good workes,</hi> was <hi>Almes.</hi> Before wee come to doctrine, wee muſt conſider ſomething of the nature of <hi>Almes.</hi> In the generall nature, <hi>Almes</hi> is a gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto thoſe that want; but yet not euery giuing, no not where there is neede, is <hi>Almes,</hi> vnleſſe it bee a <hi>Giuing</hi> ſo conditioned as the word of God preſcribes. The <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi> which the Scripture warrants, to the end it may bee called an <hi>Almes,</hi> muſt thus bee qualified: Firſt, It muſt bee with diſcretion. <hi>A good man is mercifull, &amp;c. and will meaſure his affaires by iudgement</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 112.5</note>. Many a good duty is marred in the handling. Diſcretion reſpecteth either the quantitie which is giuen, or the parties to whom: For the quantitie, a due reſpect muſt be had to a mans owne <hi>abilitie</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 11.19.</note>. The Heathen fitly compareth giuing of <hi>Almes,</hi> or any the like communicating o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee, vnto the reaching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth of ones candle, that by it another may light his, wherein care muſt bee had,<note place="margin">Nihilominus v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat.</note> that a mans owne goe not out. <hi>Charitie is bountifull</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 13 4.</note>, but not prodigall: although caſes alſo may bee in which this proportion muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded: according as the Churches of <hi>Macedonia, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng beyond their power</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.3.</note>. But this cloſe handed age gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16515:10"/>
no great cauſe to preſſe this rule, yet it muſt not bee omitted. Another branch of diſcretion is concerning the partie, to whom. For this <hi>Giuing</hi> to all without diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is not <hi>Almes. Bleſſed is the man that iudgeth wiſely of the poore</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 41.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. There is a generation to which a man ought not to giue, vnleſſe in a caſe of manifeſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: <hi>Hee that workes not, ſhould not eat</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">2. Theſ 3.10.</note>. The principall and firſt reſpect muſt bee to the <hi>Houſhold of Faith</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gal 6 10.</note>, and that <hi>the bowels of the poore Saints may bee comforted</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philem 7.</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri &amp; affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu &amp; eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Bernard.</note> To ſuch, a man muſt giue both more affectionately, and more liberally. The honeſt poore, the induſtrious poore, thoſe that fall into pouertie, not thoſe that make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of beggerie. This is diſcretion. Secondly, it muſt bee with Iuſtice. The word which in <hi>Matthew</hi> 6. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.<note place="margin">See Beza vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place.</note> is tranſlated <hi>Almes,</hi> ſignifieth Iuſtice, becauſe it is not indeede <hi>Charitie,</hi> if it doe not proceede from <hi>Equitie.</hi> Now I call that <hi>Iustice</hi> in giuing, when a man <hi>giueth of his owne. Caſt thy bread, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Eccl. 11.1.</note>. <hi>I the Lord loue iudgement: but I hate robberie for burnt offering</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 61 8.</note>: as when men ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make a kinde of ſatisfaction for a great deale of vniuſt getting, by ſome largeſſe to the poore. Thirdly, it muſt bee with compaſſion: (<hi>as if yee were alſo afflicted, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">2. Heb. 13 3.</note>). This is that which is called <hi>Tender-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eph 4 31.</note>, and, <hi>a pouring out of the ſoule to the hungrie</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 58.10.</note>. Fourthly, It muſt bee with cheerefulneſſe. <hi>God loueth a cheerefull giuer</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 9.7.</hi> Beneficentia on beneuolentia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anare deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Affectus tuus n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>men imponit operi t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Amb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</hi>
               </note>. Well doing muſt proceed from well-willing: Such as is the affection, ſuch is the action. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, It muſt be with ſimplicitie <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 12.8.</hi> Danda benefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>randa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</note>. It is done in ſimplicitie, when the approouing of our ſelues vnto God is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſcope. <hi>Almes</hi> muſt be giuen, not put out to vſe. The moſt of that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I haue now ſaid touching this <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Charitie,</hi> is comprehended in a certaine deuice or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatiue picture which I read of, of late, <note n="*" place="margin">In the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of R. M. vpon. Gen 18.32.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Charitie</hi> is po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in the likeneſſe of a naked childe, with a mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie countenance, couered in a lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, with a bloudie heart in the hand, giuing hony to a Bee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16515:11"/>
without wings. Firſt, a childe, becauſe the charitable muſt bee humble as a <hi>Childe</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Math. 18.4.</note>. Secondly, naked, <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſeeketh not her owne</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.5.</note>. Thirdly, looking merrily: <hi>Charitie reioiceth in the truth</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note>. Fourthly, couered with a cloud. <hi>Charitie</hi> hunteth not for applauſe. <hi>The right hand must not know what the left hand doth</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Math 6 3.</note>. Fifthly, A heart in the hand: <hi>Charitie</hi> is no diſſembler; the heart and hand doe agree. Sixthly, It giueth hony to a Bee without wings. It helpeth not the droane, but the Bee; not the ideler, but the labourer, whom God hath diſabled to bee his owne ſupplie. So then this is the effect of all touching <hi>Dorcas.</hi> Shee was zealous of <hi>Good Workes</hi> generally; more particularly, ſhee was a diſcreet, iuſt, compaſſionate, cheerefull, ſimple-hearted Almoner. Whatſoeuer ſhee did, ſhee did as a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> according to the preſcript of that holy doctrine, wherein ſhee was trained. Other manner of <hi>Giuing</hi> then this, the word of God could neuer teach her.</p>
            <p>Now come wee to the doctrine, which is thus: <hi>That, giuing to the poore is a ſpeciall practiſe of true Chriſtianitie, which wee may not neglect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The 3. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> Wherefore are wee told of <hi>Dorcas Almes,</hi> but to binde vs to the like vertue? It is a matter which the Scripture laboureth to faſten to vs with a three-fold cord. Firſt, Precept: Secondly, Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Thirdly, Benefit. The firſt, to enio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne vs: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, to direct vs: the third, to encourage vs. Firſt for Precept: <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters, Giue a portion to ſeuen, and alſo to eight</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 11.1.2.</note>. <hi>Is not this the faſt, that I haue choſen, to deale thy bread to the hungrie? &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 58.7.</note>. <hi>If one of thy brethren with thee bee poore, &amp;c. thou ſhalt not harden thy heart, nor ſhut thy hand from thy poore brother: but thou ſhalt open thine hand vnto him, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Deu. 15.7.8.</note>. <hi>Giue to him that asketh, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 5.4.2.</note>. <hi>Hee that hath two coats, let him giue to him that hath none; and hee that hath meat, let him doe likewiſe</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 3.11.</note>. <hi>As yee abound in euery thing, in Faith, in word, &amp;c. ſo ſee that you abound in this grace alſo</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.7.</note>. <hi>Bee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16515:11"/>
to diſtribute</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.11</note>. Thus for precept. As for examples, wee haue the Hoſpitalitie of <hi>Abraham</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 18.1.</note>, and <hi>Lot</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.1.</note>, the charitie of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> that kept an hundred Prophets vpon his owne charge in the time of perſecution vnder <hi>Iezabel</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 11.4</note>, the bountie of <hi>Iob, I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies to the blind, feet to the lame</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Iob. 19.15 16.</note>: <hi>I haue not eat my morſels alone, &amp;c. I haue ſeene none periſh for want of clothing: the lomes of the poore have bleſſed mee, becauſe hee was warmed with the fleece of my ſheepe</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Iob 31.17. &amp;c.</note>. The liberalitie of <hi>Zacheus: The halfe of my goods I giue to the poore</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 19 8.</note>. The free heartedneſſe of <hi>Cornelius: Hee gaue much Almes</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Act. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. The compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateneſſe of <hi>Philemon: By thee brother the bowels of the Saints are comforted</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Philem. 7.</note>. The forwardneſſe of <hi>Paul: Which thing</hi> (ſpeaking of remembring the poore) <hi>I was diligent to doe</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 2.10.</note>. Aboue all, wee haue the example of examples, the practiſe of Chriſt Ieſus. Generally this is noted of him, that <hi>being rich, for our ſakes hee became poore, that wee through his pouertie might bee made rich</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 8 9.</note>. Particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, though hee himſelfe liued by contribution, yet hee gaue out a ſhare to the poore <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 13.29.</note>. Heere are examples. Now for benefit and good that followeth heerein: Firſt, wee are aſſured, that whatſoeuer fleſh and bloud may imagine, yet that which is giuen is not loſt: <hi>After many daies thou ſhalt finde it</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eccle. 11.1.</note>. <hi>Hee that hath mercy vpon the poore, lendeth to the Lord, and the Lord will recompence, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pro 19.17.</note>. <hi>The liberall perſon ſhall haue plentie, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pro. 11.25.</note>. <hi>Hee that ſoweth liberally, ſhall reape liberally</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 9.6.</note>. So that heere is one good turne, a man is ſure this way to bee no loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, rather hee prouides a ſtocke for himſelfe againſt the time of neede. Secondly, heereby a man brings vpon himſelfe a continuall bleſſing thorowout his whole life. <hi>The Lord ſhall deliuer him in the time of trouble: the Lord will keepe him, and preſerue him aliue, hee ſhall bee bleſſed vpon earth, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal 41 12. &amp;c.</note>. Hee bringeth a bleſſing alſo vpon his poſteritie. <hi>His ſeede enioteth the bleſſing</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 37.26.</note>. Thirdly, this is a meanes to bring vs to the right vſe of our wealth.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16515:12"/>
               <hi>Giue almes and behold all ſhall bee cleane vnto you</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 11.41.</note>. It is like the aduiſe of a Phyſitian to helpe a ſurfet by forbearance, ſo (ſaith Chriſt) you that haue beene giuen to oppreſſion and cruelty, if you ſhall repent heereof and make knowne the truth of your repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by the fruites of Charitie, this will bee a good medicine againſt greedineſſe, and a meanes to bring you to the pure vſe of Gods bleſſings. Fourthly, it is a good pledge to a mans ſoule of his future inheritance. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it a <hi>good foundation againſt the time to come</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.19.</note>: not that our Saluation is built vpon <hi>Almes,</hi> but the bowels of compaſſion in vs towards others, is (as it were) a print or ſtamp of the mercy of God ſet vpon our hearts. Thus wee ſee how <hi>Almes g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g</hi> is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to vs in the Scripture. I could adde the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie annexed to the contrarie. <hi>Hee that ſtoppeth his eare, at the crie of the poore, hee ſhall likewiſe crie, and not bee heard</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pro. 11.13.</note>: <hi>Iudgement mercileſſe to him that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no Iudgement</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iam. 2.13.</note>. The vſe and exhortation ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Vſe.</note>Be pleaſed I pray you to giue entertainement to this point alſo. It deſerueth to bee harboured. It is the glorie of a <hi>Chriſtian, Hee hath diſtributed and giuen to the poore, his horne ſhall bee exalted with honour</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 112.9.</note>. As it deſerueth harbour, ſo wee doe generally neede to be perſwaded to open our doores to ſo worthy a gueſt. Fruites of mercy in theſe daies are exceeding ſcarce: The contrarie euils, oppreſſion, violence, gaping ouer the heads of the Poore, deuouring widowes houſes, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the poore for olde ſhooes, rackings, enhaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings, gripings, vſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, immoderate takings: theſe things, <hi>depart not from our ſtreetes</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 55 11.</note>. The portion of the poore is ſpent away in gaming, in reuelling, in contending, in gay cloathing, in ſmoke, in dogges, in drinking &amp;c. How much is vented away by ſuch meanes, by which many a poore ſoule might bee comforted,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16515:12"/>
many a priſoner ranſomed, many a decaied labourer, and induſtrious husbandman reſtored, many a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Student in the Vniuerſitie maintained, many an impoueriſhed and ſpoiled Church re-endowed, many an Hoſpitall for the ſicke and aged erected, many an houſe of correction for the ſturdie and incorrigible, builded. I am euen aſhamed for our vnfruitfulneſſe: but, eſpecially I cannot but pitie that pitifull account, which men will make, when they ſhall come at the day of the great Audite, to giue in their billes of expenſe to the Lord Paramount, to whom for theſe things we muſt bee countable. Alas, alas, how ſhall men looke the Lord in the face, when there ſhall bee ſeene ſuch large ſummes, about vanities, about contentions at Law, about buildings, about belly-cheere, about the furtherance of wicked pleaſures, nay (perhaps) ſo much to the maintenance of ſecret whoredomes, ſo much to the commuting of puniſhments, ſo much to the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and ſhifting of vnlawfull iſſues, and ſo little, ſo nothing, to holy vſes, to the Church of Chriſt, and to the Saints of Chriſt. Thinke vpon it, I intreat you, and propound this vertuous woman for an example: and as in other particulars, ſo remember to follow her in this: That which you will doe in this kinde, put it not off vntill your latter end. Theſe her <hi>Almes,</hi> were fruits of her life courſe, not of her Legacies at her death. <hi>While wee haue time, let vs doe good, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note>. I condemne not funerall beneficence ſimply: onely I preferre the vitall before it. They which doe nothing but by way of a teſtamentarie beneuolence, are right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſaid to bee men of good willes, but of euill deedes. Thus farre of the life of <hi>Dorcas.</hi> Now of her death, verſe 37. <hi>It came to paſſe, in thoſe daies, that ſhe was ſicke,<note place="margin">The ſecond part.</note> and died.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot ſpeake at large of euery thing I muſt ſtill (as hitherto) ſelect the principall; and that in this part
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16515:13"/>
is this:<note place="margin">The fourth Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>That euen the holiest and most religious among the ſonnes of men are ſubiect vnto death. Dorcas,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſhee was a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> notwithſtanding ſhee was zealous of <hi>Good Workes,</hi> and full of <hi>Almes-deedes,</hi> yet heere in thoſe daies ſhee ſickened and was dead. This may eaſily bee inſtanced by a World of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Righteous <hi>Noah,</hi> faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> zealous <hi>Lot,</hi> meeke <hi>Moſes,</hi> religious <hi>Dauid,</hi> innocent <hi>Iob,</hi> painfull <hi>Paul,</hi> penitent <hi>Zache,</hi> charitable <hi>Cornelius,</hi> all the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the firſt times, and whomſoeuer elſe the word of God hath well reported of, where are they? Are they not all dead? Doe they not all ſee corruption? Are they not all gone downe into the ſlimie Valley? Haue they not long ſince made their bed in the darke? None of them all was able to deliuer his life from the power of the graue. How is it then true (will ſome ſay) that Chriſt hath deſtroied death, ſith death hath ſtill power ouer Gods Saints? I anſwer: Chriſt did not die to take away death (as yet) but to change death: not to ouerthrow the being of death, but to plucke out <hi>the ſting of Death</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 15 55</note>: not quite to ſtop vp the graue, but to remooue and quell the victorie of the graue. The holieſt therefore doe ſtill die, but death cannot ſting them, the graue cannot triumph ouer them. Death in it ſelfe is the way to Hell: It is altered to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of grace, and become a Portall by which the ſoule paſſeth from out of the bodie into Heauen. Death in it ſelfe is as a Sergeant to arreſt, and to bring to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but to the elect of God, it is as the Angell which guided <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Act 12.</note>, and leadeth them from the vale of Teares into the land of Righteouſneſſe. Thus the Holy die, but not to damnation, for to them which are in Chriſt, <hi>there is no damnation</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. It is a piece of their happineſſe that they die: <hi>Except the wheat corne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all into the ground, and die, it bideth alone</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 12.24.</note>, and, <hi>oh foole, that which thou ſoweſt is not quickned except it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16515:13"/>
die</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.35</note>. A foole or a childe ſeeing a goodly cluſter of grapes, thinketh it pity to put them into the preſſe, and to deface them, but hee that is wiſe knoweth that by this meanes, the liquor in them is preſerued, and that this timely gathering is a meanes of keeping from corruption: So wee thinke ſometime, <hi>Oh, it is pity ſuch an one ſhould die ſo ſoone;</hi> as one might haue ſaid of <hi>Dorcas, alas ſo good a woman, ſo pitifull a creature can ill bee ſpared:</hi> But God in his wiſedome knoweth it to bee good, and if hee cut of the life of good <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> as it were in the middle of the ſtemme, doubtleſſe it is, that <hi>his eyes may not ſee the euill to come</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">2. King. 22.20. The Vſe.</note>.</p>
            <p>The ſpeciall vſe I will driue this point vnto, is to vrge vpon vs all a due meditation of our end. For ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if euen the holieſt die, then all muſt die. If death ſeaze <hi>euen vpon the houſe of God, where ſhall the vngodly and ſinners appeare?</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.18</note>. If <hi>Dorcas</hi> doe die, ſurely <hi>Iezabel</hi> ſhall not eſcape: If the tender hearted women that wept for Chriſt, then the ſtonie-hearted men, that ſcoffed at Chriſt; if thoſe that embalmed him, then thoſe that buffered him: if ſhee that poured ointment on his head, then hee that ſpate in his face: there is no auoidance: It <hi>is appointed vnto Men that they ſhall once die</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note>. It is heauens decree, and it cannot bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked. And what is that to die? to be no more? No; happie then were <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> and happie you, that now make a mocke of ſinne; but, to bee ſtill for euer either in endleſneſſe of bliſſe, or perpetuity of woe. What ſhall wee then doe? ſhall wee reaſon as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, <hi>Let vs eate and drinke, for to morrow wee ſhall die</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.32</note>? God forbid: that were to bee like the Diuell, whoſe maner is to play reaxe and to haue <hi>great wrath when hee hath but a ſhort time</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Reu 12.12.</note>, or ſhall wee gull our owne ſoules, and <hi>put far away the euill day</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Amos 6.3.</note>, and dreame of many yeares like the Rich <hi>Foole</hi> in the Goſpell <note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 12.19.</note>? Farre bee theſe things from vs; let vs rather endeuour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16515:14"/>
by this to <hi>apply our hearts to wiſedome</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal 90 12.</note>: and what wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? verily in a word, the skanning of this one point often in our mindes,<note place="margin">Hinc ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quo tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ium?</note> 
               <hi>Hence I muſt, and whither then?</hi> like men that trauell, who bee no ſooner come to their lodging, but they are talking of their next Inne. The debatement of this queſtion in the minde would bring forth an excellent fruit, euen, a care to bee aſſured of admiſſion <hi>into euerlaſting habitation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.9.</note>. A man would thus reaſon. <hi>I muſt remoue and whither then? Hell is my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, how ſhall I eſcape it? Heauen is the only place, how ſhall I come to it:</hi> Thus one good thought would make way for another, and lead vs on by degrees to that which we do moſt neglect, <hi>(the prouiding for the future eſtate.) Oh that we were wiſe to vnderſtand this,</hi> and <hi>that we would conſider our later end</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Deu. 32.29.</note>, or that we did conceiue the happineſſe and ſweete comfort of a prepared and long expected end? This promiſed, the day of death, a godly man may ſay of it when it commeth, as the people trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly ſometime ſpake of the day of <hi>Dauids</hi> corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſa. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.24</note>. The children of God whoſe care hath beene to <hi>keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnſpotted of the World</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iam. 1 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> may call death, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did the place where hee came, <hi>Mahanaim,</hi> becauſe there the <hi>Angels met him</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 32.2.</note>, ſo there, thoſe <hi>Miniſtring ſpirits which are ſent forth for their good which bee heires of life</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> ſhall receiue their ſoules to beare them into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams boſome</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 16.22</note>. Oh that Religion and godlineſſe might bee more ſweet vnto vs, which will bring a man ſuch peace at the laſt. <hi>As for the wicked, it is not ſo with them</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 1.4.</note>. In their death they be like vnto him, of whom the Prophet ſpeakes, who <hi>did flee from a Lyon and a Beare met him</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Am. 5 9.</note>, they eſcape one miſery, and irrecouerably fall into an other. This life hath (it may be) afflicted them with rods, but death ſhall come vpon them with ſcorpions. God ſhall ſhut them from his tabernacle and not ſuffer them to come neere the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16515:14"/>
Oh that wee could make haſt to <hi>breake of our ſinnes</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Dan. 4.24.</note> by repentance, which will bring ſo much woe at the laſt. This is the vſe. <hi>Dorcas</hi> is dead, the holieſt muſt die: if holineſſe muſt yeeld, profanenes cannot ſtand out, whither holy or profane all muſt die, and come to iudgement. <hi>Let him that is holy bee holy ſtill</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Reu 22.11.</note>, and <hi>hold faſt that none may take his crowne</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Reu 3.11.</note>. Let him that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, I will not ſay bee profane ſtill, but let him <hi>caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his tranſgreſſions, for why will yee die oh houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. 18 31.</hi> Nullus peniten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiae locus, nullus ſatisfactionis effectus. Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ad Demetrium. Non Job, non Daniel, non Noe, rogare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſunt, &amp;c. Hiero.</note>? Yet there is hope, but if wee bee once ſtept ouer the threſhold of death, there is no place for repentance, no vſe of any Satisfaction: If <hi>Iob, Noah, Daniel</hi> ſhould entreate for vs, God would not heare vs. So an end of this admonition touching our end, which if we ſuffer it to die in our thoughts, we ſhall ſurely die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
